當你遭遇嚴寒侵襲時
When the cold comes for you,
血液會停止流向四肢
the blood stops running to your limbs.
它會流向軀干 保持臟器溫暖
It pools up inside to keep your organs warm.
這是我的初戀情人告訴我的
My first love told me that.
他是個海上勞工 高高瘦瘦 體格強健
An offshore roughnecker he was. Tall and lean, and tough as whitleather.
他會說：“魯絲 你的微笑讓我溫暖
He'd say, "Ruthie, your smile keeps me warm."
所以千萬要保持微笑 直到我回來”
"So be sure to wear it till I'm home."
-好 我們走吧 -好
- Let's go. - Right.
-走起來 -好
- Move it. - Okay.
沒錯 那玩意兒很厲害
Uh, yeah, that was some shit.
接著 嚴寒就會侵襲你的思想
Next, the cold comes for your mind.
然后是你的意志力
And after that, your will.
不過
And yet still,
你的心依然在抗爭
the heart fights on.
是魯絲
Ruth.
她說威爾福德正在車尾搞什么勾當
She says Wilford's up to something in the back.
她走之后就沒了陽光
♪ Ain't no sunshine when she's gone ♪
她不在時就沒了溫暖
♪ It's not warm when she's away ♪
她走之后就沒了陽光
♪ Ain't no sunshine When she's gone ♪
而她總是離開得太久
♪ And she's always gone too long ♪
每次她離開
♪ Anytime she goes away ♪
朋友們 今天是大日子
Big day, friends.
確實是大日子 先生 測試需要的一切都準備好了
- Big day, sir. - Everything's ready for the test.
可憐的黑得伍德醫生 親愛的
Dear, poor Dr. Headwood.
你那可憐的丈夫 黑得伍德醫生去世后 你還好嗎
How are you doing without our dear, poor Dr. Headwood?
我感覺他依然跟我們在一起 先生
I feel he's still with us, sir.
接手他以前的工作 你有信心嗎
Are you confident here, in his shoes as it were?
絕對有 先生
Hundred percent.
對了 您看這身衣服行嗎  很有“曼哈頓計劃”的風范
Yes, how is this for the occasion? It's very, um, Manhattan Project.
挺好
Fine, fine.
放下棉絨刷 把毛巾遞給我
Put down the lint brush and hand me my towel.
我失陪了 我們有很多工作要做
Pardon me. We do have much to do.
謝謝
Thank you.
我那位海上勞工戀人過早地離開了我
He left me too soon, my roughneck love.
他工作的鉆井平臺塌了 所有的人都沉入了海底
His rig went down with every man aboard.
我知道在他獨自漂浮時 我的微笑讓他感到溫暖
I know my smile kept him warm as he floated, all alone.
我也知道 在威爾福德這列 1023節車廂組成的列車上
Just as I know our hearts will be the last thing to go
我們的心將會是
on Wilford's train.
最后屈服的東西
1,023 cars long.
她有脫水癥狀 營養不良 而且血壓很低
She's, um, dehydrated, malnourished, her blood pressure's low.
她可能有輻射中毒 所以…
She's probably got radiation poisoning, so…
嘿 想不想談談 在外面發生的那件事
Hey. You wanna talk about what happened out there?
想 你們倆差點就沒命了
Yeah, when you two almost died.
不是那個 是我們接吻的事
No, when we kissed.
我馬上就要當爸爸了 而且我答應過扎拉
I got a baby on the way, and I made a promise to Zarah.
-我不需要談那件事 -好 我也不需要
- I don't need to talk about it. - No, me either.
本拿到數據了 要不要去看看 這番鬧騰是否值得
Ben's got the data. Shall we see if it's been worth it?
好的
Yeah. Yes.
我還是不明白 她怎么可能在外面生存八年
I still don't get how it's possible to survive eight years out there.
用冰把自己封在室內
You freeze yourself in.
隨著反應堆冷卻 靠剩余的電力維持生命
Live off the residual power as the reactor cools.
要我說 這辦法太有才了
It's kind of genius if you ask me.
你當初出去 都不是為了找她
It's not even why you went out there in the first place.
沒錯
No.
（宜居區）
結果出來了
We have our results.
我估計這表情 不光是因為你的肋骨疼吧
Guessing that grimace isn't just from the ribs.
跟之前的差不多
More of the same.
分析顯示該區域正在變暖
Analysis shows location is warming,
但變化速度不夠快 暫時還不宜居住
but the trend isn't steep enough to be habitable yet.
那要等多久呢 本
How long are we talking, Ben?
-一個世紀  -差不多吧
- A century? - Give or take.
已經是第五個點了 還是不行
Well, that's O-for-five on this milk run.
好吧 那就只剩最后一個地點了
Okay, that leaves one more location.
阿拉伯的那個暖點
Your Arabian warm spot.
對 從我們迄今為止 采集到的所有數據來看
Yeah. From all the data we've collected so far,
那個地方實際上很有希望
it looks actually pretty promising.
它位于這里 非洲之角 阿拉伯半島以南
Located here, Horn of Africa, southern Arabian Peninsula.
本 我們的食物不夠了 撐不到那里的
We haven't enough food to get there.
-現在我們又多了一張嘴 -該去奪回我們的列車了
- We've got another mouth to feed. - It's time to get our train back.
我們找到他們 重新連接列車 然后帶大家一起去新的暖點
We find them, reconnect to the train, we lead everybody to the new hot spot.
跟奪回列車相比 我更擔心奪回后能否保住它
I'm far less concerned with taking her, than keeping her.
她說得沒錯 我們這可是空手而歸啊
She's right. We're going back empty-handed.
沒有新伊甸園存在的證據
- No proof of New Eden.
也沒有梅蘭妮
- No Melanie.
我們不是空手而歸
We're not empty-handed.
遠非如此
Far from it.
嘿
Hey.
醒醒 嘿
Come on. Hey.
好吧 別 沒事的 我能行
Okay. No, it's okay. I got it.
嘿 別緊張 沒事的 一切都好
Hey, no, you're all right. Hey, you're all right.
聽著 在這里 不需要穿防護服 看到嗎
Look, you don't need the suit here. See?
嗯 沒事了
It's all right, yeah.
你好
Uh, hi.
我叫安德烈雷頓
My name's Andre Layton.
我們算是見過面了 在核電站時我們打了一架
We kind of met already, uh, fighting in the nuclear plant.
記得嗎 對不起 你會說英語嗎
You remember that? I'm sorry, do you speak English?
會
Yeah?
給
Here.
好
Okay.
好點了
All right?
你叫什么名字
What's your name?
-阿莎 -阿莎
- Asha. - Asha.
很好
Great.
別擔心 你在這里是安全的
Don't worry, you're safe here.
沒人會傷害你 你在雪國列車上
No one's gonna hurt you, you're on Snowpiercer.
雪國列車
Snowpiercer?
我是在做夢嗎
Am I… Am I dreaming?
除非我們大家都在做夢
Not unless we all are.
-那列車幸存下來了  -我帶你去看看吧 你能走嗎
- The train survived? - Let me show you. Can you walk?
就在上面
Just up here.
-她是什么人  -你已經沒資格提問了
Who is that? You lost the privilege to ask questions.
得了 貝絲 他們之前是在外面嗎
Oh, come on, Bess. Were they outside?
你的腦袋怎么樣 估計很疼吧
How's your head? Bet it hurts.
沒你打斷我鼻梁骨時那么疼
Not as bad as when you broke my nose.
那個偉大的工程師威爾福德先生呢
Where's Mr. Wilford, the Great Engineer?
我們其實不知道 現在有兩列列車了
Uh, yeah, we don't know. There's two trains now.
樓下有一個女人被關在一間牢房里
There's a woman in a cage.
這故事又長又復雜 你也有故事 我很想聽
It's a long, complicated story. You've got one too, and I wanna hear it,
不過 目前最好是 一次消化一件事 相信我
but it's better to take one thing at a time right now, trust me.
我憑什么要相信這些
Why should I trust any of this?
歡迎登車 阿莎
Welcome aboard, Asha.
釋放10%應該就能引起震撼 卻不會致命
Ten percent should give us a nice jolt. Nothing too lethal.
這個水平很適合測試 先生
An appropriate test level, sir.
撤空的頭等車廂
And the decommissioned First Class cars
應該能為電磁脈沖的沖擊 提供必要的緩沖
should provide the necessary buffer from the EMP pulse.
好了 凱文 我們來聽它“一展歌喉”吧
Well, let's hear her sing, Kevin.
開始測試 釋放10%
Commence trial. Ten percent.
確認 釋放10%
Confirmed, ten percent.
開始倒計時
Initiate countdown.
都準備好了
We're all clear.
倒計時開始
Initiating countdown.
兩分鐘
Two minutes.
我把你的小朋友帶回來了
Brought your little friend back.
我們不是該離開這里嗎
Shouldn't we get out of here?
我敢打賭那是某種武器
I'd wager that it's a weapon.
它設在最后一節車廂里 那是列車重新連接的地方
It's set in the very last car, right where the trains need to reconnect.
你確定不會只是一個加熱器嗎
Are you sure it's not just a heater?
-你沒事吧  -沒事 謝謝關心 我只是冷
- You all right? - Yes, thanks. I'm just cold.
所以你不該在外面跑
That's why you can't be running around out there.
我們不能失去你
We can't afford to lose you.
要是整天躲在洞里 我還有什么用
I'm no use to anyone hiding in a hole, am I?
倒數五、四
And in five, four,
三、二…
three, two…
沒事了
It's all right.
剛才那是什么
What was that?
感覺像某種電波從我體內穿過
Felt like some electrical wave went through me.
我想這就是那個武器了
I think that was the thing.
干得漂亮 凱文 大家干得都漂亮
Well done, Kevin. Well done, crew.
太好了
Yes!
-奧斯 這是怎么回事  -就…
- Oz, what's going on? - Just…
給我一點時間 我想…
Just give me a second. I wanna…
我想記住這一刻
I wanna remember this.
LJ…
這個世界很無情
it's a mean old world,
但是有了你
but with you in it,
它終于有了意義
it finally makes sense.
小萊拉
Lilah Junior,
你愿意嫁給我嗎
will you marry me?
老天啊 這顆鉆石真大
Holy shit, that rock is huge!
可不是 說來你可能不信 這可能是世上現存的最大的鉆石了
I know. It's actually crazy. It's probably the biggest diamond left in the world.
-只用一雙厚襪子就換來了 -快給我戴上
- All it cost was a pair of heavy socks. - Put it on me.
你得先說“我愿意”才行
You gotta say yes first.
我愿意
Yes, yes.
父母去世后 我以為不會再有人愛我了
I didn't think anyone would love me after my parents died.
我知道 寶貝 我知道
I know, baby. I know.
我們得告訴威爾福德
We have to tell Wilford.
不是吧
Really?
是的 出于尊重
Yes. Out of respect.
他就像我的家人一樣 我的意思是…
He's the closest thing I have to family. I mean…
除了你以外
After you now.
好吧
Okay.
小萊拉和奧斯威勒先生來了 他們想見你
Lilah Junior and Mr. Osweiller are here to see you.
帶他們進來
Ah, bring them.
他戴著領帶呢
- He's wearing a tie. - Mmm?
我年輕的夜車居民們
My young denizens of the Nightcar.
-我們能私下談談… -我們要結婚了
- Could we have a word in private-- - We're getting married.
-什么  -我們想第一個告訴您
- What? - We wanted you to be the first to know.
LJ 親愛的 這真是驚喜啊
LJ, my dear, what a surprise.
給她戴上這么漂亮的戒指 是一項明智之舉 奧斯威勒先生
Very wise to put such a nice ring on her finger, Mr. Osweiller.
我們有多久沒舉辦過婚禮了
When was the last time we had a wedding?
這可是大事情
This is quite the occasion.
或許正是列車此刻所需要的
Perhaps just the occasion the train needs.
不 我們沒想大肆操辦
No, we're not expecting anything.
-我們甚至都不… -我想
- We don't even-- - I am.
你應該辦一場大婚禮 親愛的 人生的這一程太艱苦了
And you should, my dear. Life's been so bloody dreary this leg.
我們會允許所有人都歇一個班次
We'll give everyone a shift off.
提醒一下那些抱怨的人 團結是什么樣子的
Let's remind all the grumblers what unity looks like.
提醒他們我們是同一列列車上的 忠誠會得到回報
That we're all in this together, and loyalty is rewarded.
你覺得怎么樣
- What do you think?
稍微歇口氣對大家有好處
- We could all use a little respite.
-或許可以多分一兩份口糧… -太好了 那就定在明天
- Maybe an extra ration or-- - Wonderful. Tomorrow then.
明天
Tomorrow?
是呀 有何不可 沒時間臨陣退縮
Yeah. Why not? No time for cold feet.
LJ 我們要讓夜車煥然一新
We'll transform the Nightcar, LJ.
或者我該稱呼你為 “奧斯威勒太太”
Or should I say, Mrs. Osweiller?
弗爾杰-奧斯威勒
- Oh… Folger-Osweiller? - Um…
非常順口 我要用層層的紅色天鵝絨來布置
Rolls off the tongue. I'm seeing red velvet, layers.
扎拉 去找糕點師
Ah… Zarah, go see the Cakemaker.
-你把糕點師貶入堆肥區了 -那就把他弄出來 我們要舉辦婚禮
- You put the Cakemaker in Compost. - Then get him out. We're getting married.
（忠臣大婚 ）
給他沖個澡 他做糕點需要什么 就去面包房拿 明白嗎
Get him a shower and anything he needs from the bakery, okay?
謝謝
Thank you. Thank you.
（全列車公假）
你在這里干什么
What the hell are you doing here?
威爾福德在造武器 你知道這事嗎
Wilford's building a weapon. You know anything about that?
我知道他在策劃什么 但不知道武器的事
I know he's up to something, but no.
魯絲看到哈維在制造那個武器 所以她想跟他取得聯系
Well, Ruth saw Javi working on it, so she wants to make contact with him.
我告訴過你們了 哈維不愿跟我說話
I told you guys, Javi won't talk to me.
自從被那只狗咬過之后 他整個人就變了
He hasn't been the same since that dog attack.
誰沒個傷疤呢  這是魯絲的決定 她想見他
Well, we all got scars. It's Ruth's call. She wants to see him.
砸顯示器也不會讓衛星與地球同步
Hitting the monitor does not tend to affect the satellite's geosync.
但能讓我感覺好受些 不過我們大家都不在狀態
What it does do is make me feel better, but we're all falling out of orbit.
本 我們要怎么在大海里撈到針呢
How do you find a needle in a haystack?
謝天謝地 只是一片大海而已
Thank God, it's only a haystack.
-你有什么見解嗎  -只有一個
- You have any theories? - I have one theory.
他在跟蹤我們
That he is following us?
這一心理假設真不錯啊
That's a pretty good psychological assumption.
我們將在一天左右回到主軌道 經過這里時
If he is following us, we're back on the main line in a day or so.
我們的衛星覆蓋范圍會有所改善 如果他在跟蹤我們
As we came through here, our satellite coverage improved.
或許我們就能探測到他
Maybe we see him then.
他也能探測到我們
And he sees us?
你媽媽要是看到你昨天 駕馭列車時的表現 會很驕傲的
Your mum would be proud of how you handled the train yesterday.
我并不這么認為 本 不過謝謝你這么說
I don't really think so, Ben, but thank you.
艾莉 我們找到了一個幸存者
Alex, we found a survivor.
也許希望出現奇跡并無不可
Maybe we can hope for a miracle.
她已經死了 本
She's gone, Ben.
我可以接受
It's all right.
嘿
Hey.
跟我說說她是誰
Tell me who she is.
至少告訴我你在找什么
At least tell me what you're looking for.
（沙特阿拉伯 蘇丹）
你找到了什么
What did you find?
（又做了一個夢）
就在這里
Just, uh, in here.
（乘務員）
我為你布置了一下
I've made it up for you.
真暖和啊
It's, uh… It's so warm.
-謝謝你… -我叫喬西
- Thank you, uh… - Josie.
喬西
Josie. Josie.
不好意思 我已經很久沒說話了
Sorry, it's, uh… It's been a long time since I spoke.
沒事 會慢慢熟練起來的
It's all right. It'll all come back.
你活下來了 我的意思是…
You made it. I mean… Wow.
你沒事吧
You all right?
嗨
Hey.
你還好嗎
You all right?
你離被凍死最近的一次有多近
How close you ever come to freezing to death?
跟多數人差不多吧
I guess no less than most of us.
那經歷跟大家說的一樣嗎
Is it like they say?
是的
Yeah.
你開始放松 開始覺得暖和
You start to relax. It goes warm.
會看到一些東西
You see things.
好吧
Okay.
比如說樹
Like, uh, trees?
龍血樹 青草
Dragon's blood tree. Grass.
我能感覺到陽光
I could feel the sun.
那是我們在找的地方
It was the place we're looking for.
很高興你活過來了 因為那不是我們在找的地方
Well, I'm glad you came back 'cause it wasn't.
不 聽著 這種樹只在亞丁灣生長
No, look, these trees only grow in the Gulf of Aden,
亞丁灣就在阿拉伯暖點的中間
right here in the middle of our Arabian warm spot.
我以前從沒聽說過龍血樹
I'd never even heard of a dragon's blood tree before,
可我卻看到了它
but I saw it.
你是說你看到了未來
Are you saying you had a vision?
-我只是在告訴你當時發生的事 -你告訴過別人嗎
- I'm just telling you what happened. - You tell anyone else?
-沒有 -很好
- No. - Good.
保持正常狀態
Keep it on the rails.
你當時差點沒命了 所以記憶中的某些東西閃現了出來
You had a close call, something popped out of your memory.
高中時學過的某種樹
Some tree you learned about in high school.
是呀 你或許是對的 謝謝提點
Yeah. Yeah, you're probably right. Thanks.
嗯 好
Yeah. Okay.
和往常一樣 又經歷一次瀕死體驗 對嗎
Another day, another near-death experience, right?
好
Okay.
-我愛你 哥們 -嗯
- Love you, buddy. - Yeah.
凱文 今天我們的攻勢與往日不同
We're on a different tack today, Kevin.
我們要發起魅力攻勢
A charm offensive.
你覺得怎么樣
What do you think?
太紅了嗎
Too much red?
紅色永不嫌夠 先生
Never enough red, sir.
我同意
I agree.
-你為什么要那么說  -說什么
- Why'd you say that? - Say what?
我說什么了
What?
“弗爾杰-奧斯威勒”
"Folger-Osweiller."
我只是那么一說而已 沒想到他會記到登記簿上
I just said it. I didn't know he'd put it on the register.
是呀 這下他成了婚禮的主角
Yeah, well, it's his wedding now.
-我就知道他會這么做 -那又怎樣
- I knew he'd do this. - So what?
這一天 我們將會享受 國王和王后的待遇
We get to be king and queen of everything for a day.
他是在利用我們 LJ
He's using us, LJ.
他是在我們身上作投資
He's investing in us.
辦一場小小的儀式 我就很開心了
I would've been very happy with something small.
給你唱首歌 就幾個朋友在場 但這是不可能的 對嗎
Sing you a song, a few of us. That wasn't on the table, was it?
沒錯 因為我們沒有朋友
Yeah, because we don't have any friends.
我希望我們成為大腕夫婦 有一天我們可能會管理這列列車
I wanna be in a power couple. We could run this train one day.
-天啊 LJ  -怎么了
- LJ, Jesus! - What?
年邁的人不斷死去 都快沒有年輕人了
Old people keep dying off, there's barely any young people left.
很快 就得由我們來統領他們
And soon, we'll have to rule them.
這可是我們的婚禮啊 你就從不停止算計嗎
It's our wedding day. Do you ever stop conniving?
-算計是好事 -好吧
- Conniving is good. - Fine!
去算計吧 現在想取消已經太遲了
Connive away! It's too late to call it off now,
因為提出取消 威爾福德就會 把我的腦袋凍掉 對嗎
'cause Wilford would have my head out a port, wouldn't he?
別這樣甩手走開
Don't walk away from me!
奧斯
Oz?
哈維
Javi?
你可以跟我說話的 這里沒有別人
You can talk to me. No one is here.
工程師 威爾福德要你去頭等車廂
Engineer, Wilford wants you down in First.
可我在上班呢
But I'm on shift.
我不知道 他要你去的 所以設成自動駕駛 快去就是
I don't know. That's what he wants, so put it on autopilot and off you go.
你看上去很漂亮
You look beautiful.
今天是你的大日子
- It's your big day. - Would you leave it?
你能別去管它了嗎
I don't care if it looks like shit. Just leave it.
我不在乎它是否亂糟糟的 別去管它就是
Oh, dear. I heard the bride might be blue, but blue in the face?
天啊 我聽說過新娘子會有婚前憂郁 不知道還會大發脾氣
Excuse me.
-我先出去了 -好 那樣最好 謝謝
Yes, that will be best, thank you.
好了 來 告訴我你在為什么生氣
Now, now, here. Now, tell me what you fought about?
“你總是在算計” 他覺得我又自私又冷酷
"You're always conniving." He thinks I'm selfish and I'm cruel.
有時候我不得不那樣 不是嗎
I have to be sometimes, don't I?
所以我才想讓你待在夜車上 LJ
It's why I wanted you in the Nightcar, LJ.
你是個現實主義者 你知道有人受傷是難免的事
You're a realist. You understand someone always gets hurt.
就是 我雖然不會大聲說出來 但“這就是生活”
Yes, it's like, I don't say it out loud, but c'est la vie.
他或許還覺得 整場婚禮都被我接管了
He also probably thinks I'm taking over the whole ceremony.
你明白為什么 你們的婚禮對我很重要嗎
Do you understand why your wedding is important to me?
能幫你管束大家
Helps keep everyone in line.
沒錯 他們會看到 只有一種辦事方法 就是我的方法
Yes. They see there's only one way, the way I do things.
你看 在這列列車上 有一樣東西
You see, on the train, the old laws and morality,
比舊法和道德更重要 它是什么
they don't matter as much as… what?
-忠誠 -沒錯
- Loyalty. - That's right.
對列車的忠誠
Loyalty to the train.
好了 你這假惺惺的眼淚 留著到婚禮上流吧
Now, save the crocodile tears for the ceremony.
為了我 好好表演一番
Make a show of it, for me.
我會的
I will.
回頭見
See you soon.
婚床放在這里很不錯呀
Lovely spot for your wedding bed.
謝謝夸獎 是我們自己布置的
Thank you. We, uh, did it ourselves.
過來
Come.
坐 來啊
Sit down. Come on.
年輕激昂的愛情 我很熟悉
Young, tumultuous love, I know it well.
我指的是激昂的部分 我已經不再年輕了
Well, the tumultuous part, not the young bit anymore.
不過 LJ不開心
But LJ's upset.
是的 這個嘛…
Yeah, well, it's, uh…
是婚前緊張
Pre-wedding jitters.
我們會沒事的 是的
We'll be fine. Yeah.
我對她有很強的保護意識
Well, I am rather protective of her.
所以 我好好查閱了一下 羅齊先生的人事記錄
So I had a long look at Mr. Roche's personnel records,
你當制動員的時候 很會把握各種機會嘛
and you were an opportunistic boy in blue.
我經營過幾份副業 是的 先生
Well, ran a few side hustles. Yes, sir.
一個劣跡斑斑的企業家
Ah, an entrepreneur with a vicious streak.
這是當夜車經理的優良品質
Good qualities in a Nightcar manager.
然而…
And yet…
這雙手…
these hands…
卻能彈奏如此動聽的鋼琴曲
play piano so beautifully.
你心里有點渴望成為一名藝術家
Part of you just yearns to be an artiste,
顫聲吟唱最悲傷的歌曲
warbling the saddest of songs.
我不是在所謂的 富有創造性的環境中長大的
Well, I didn't grow up in what you'd call a creative environment.
你表達了自己的心聲
You found your voice.
鋼琴師
Piano man, hmm?
你那紅發妻子則負責吧臺
And his ginger wife behind the bar.
你們是我的團隊
You're my team here.
這點我們明白
We understand that.
真的
We do.
你們制動員搜身的手法 還記得嗎
Your Brakeman shakedown move, remember?
你也抓我的
Squeeze mine too.
來吧 抓吧
Go on. Squeeze them.
用力點
Harder.
再用力點 用上所有的勁道
Harder. Give them some basso profundo.
好 你的雙手是用來干什么的
Now, what are your hands for, hmm?
捏碎別人的蛋
Crushing balls.
還要用來愛撫你的妻子
And caressing your wife.
在那之后 你想怎么彈琴都行
When that's done, by all means, tickle the ivories.
因為你非常有才華
Because you're very talented.
這是真心話
I mean that.
文件
Papers.
包
Bag.
德拉托爾先生
Mr. De la Torre.
是我
Just me.
好久不見了
Long time no see.
魯絲 可你…
Ruth? But you…
你應該在另一列列車上呀
You're on the other train.
不 我一直都在這里 幫助乘客們
No, I've been here the whole time. I've been helping the passengers.
為我們在外面的朋友盡己所能
Doing my bit for our friends out there.
你不該在這里的
You shouldn't be here.
哈維
Oh, Javi.
-我很抱歉… -不…
- Oh, I'm sorry-- - No, no, no…
工程師 我只是要你幫忙 拜托了
Engineer, I just… I just need your help, please.
你在列車后部做的那個東西 它是什么 它能做什么
The thing that you're working on back there, what is it? What does it do?
它能徹底阻止雷頓
It's gonna stop Layton dead.
-我得回狗那里去了 抱歉 -不 先別走
- I need to go back to the dog, I'm sorry. - No, not yet.
你得告訴我它是怎么運作的
Tell me how it works.
-不  -哈維 哈維
- No. No! No! - Javi? Javi!
你美極了
Gorgeous.
歡迎 勇敢的乘客們 工人們 及其他所有人
Welcome, brave passengers, workers, all now.
我很高興大家能暫停手頭的工作
It's my great pleasure to pause our labors,
花點時間團聚在一起
and spend time in union.
今天我們匯聚一堂 是為了慶祝
The union today by marriage,
小萊拉弗爾杰 和約翰克里斯多夫奧斯威勒喜結良緣
of Lilah Folger Junior and John Christopher Osweiller.
我知道 最近這段行程 非常寒冷 供給不足
I know these have been cold miles of deprivation.
紀律嚴酷
And discipline is harsh.
你們都得了凍瘡
You've paid in frostbite,
所愛的人因流感而喪生 愿他們安息
and loved ones lost to influenza. May they rest in peace.
所以 該是慶祝勝利的時候了 不是嗎
So it's time we celebrate a win, isn't it?
傳統的婚姻
Old World matrimony.
各位 把酒杯倒滿 我們有足夠的酒 大家都有份
Everyone, fill a glass. There's enough for every soul.
還有額外的熱餐
Extra hot food too.
-我去去就回 -好
- I'll be back. - Okay.
讓全車上下 都為萊拉和約翰舉起酒杯吧
Raise a glass up and down our train for Lilah and John.
來吧 干杯
Come on. Cheers.
現在 各位
Everyone now.
再敬我們與列車牢不可破的協議
To our unbreakable pact with the train.
敬忠誠
To loyalty
以及你們與我的約定
and your contract with me.
生存
To survive.
威爾福德
Wilford! Wilford!
聽上去像是一種電磁脈沖武器
Sounds like an electromagnetic pulse weapon.
我從來沒有真正見過
Never actually seen one before.
-但你知道它的運作原理吧  -知道
- But you do know how it works? - Yeah.
它能發出電磁脈沖 破壞雪國列車上的所有電子設備
It sends out an electromagnetic pulse killing the electronics on Snowpiercer,
讓雷頓的列車無法前進
leaving Layton dead in the water.
那趁著這場婚禮 我們來設法阻止那種情況發生
So while this wedding is happening, let's try and make it not do that.
有操作手冊嗎
- You got a manual?
拜托 光明
- Come on, Lights.
我跟魯絲說你很擅長這類活兒
I told the lady you're good at this kind of thing.
解除電磁脈沖武器
Disarming EMPs?
是呀
Yeah.
干嗎
What?
哈維 你要去哪兒
Where you going, Javi?
回狗那里去
- Back to the dog. - Ah-ah.
你剛才去哪兒了
Where are you coming from?
收集最后一套數據
Final data collection.
我能走了嗎
Can I go?
跟我來
Come with me.
跟著我
Follow me.
你也是
You too.
現在 我要你們完成
Now, I ask you to take the sacred steps
與永恒機車相結合的神圣儀式
in union with the Eternal Engine.
這四步代表了人類所經歷的歷程
These four steps represent the path humanity has taken.
從青草
From grass
到寒冰
to ice.
-從寒冰到鋼鐵 -從寒冰到鋼鐵
- From ice to steel. - From ice to steel.
從鋼鐵到…
And from steel to the lights…
永恒機車的燈光
of the Eternal Engine.
有人來過這里嗎
Anyone come through here?
那個被狗咬了臉的工程師常來這里
That dog-faced engineer's here all the time.
不過他很快就會出來
But he's in and out.
我們還是要進去看看
Well, we'll check it anyway.
敵人會覺得這場婚禮 是他們行動的好時機 不是嗎
Wouldn't this wedding be a great distraction for the enemy?
我完全不知道要怎么解除這玩意兒
I have no idea how to disarm this thing.
你就各處擺弄一下唄
Just start messing with it.
-這就是你的計劃  -你才是我的計劃
- That's your plan? - You're my plan.
軍靴和待客部的人來了
Jackboots and teal coming!
-什么  -我們會被困在這里的 快離開
- What? - They'll pin us back here. Let's go.
我們得走了 快走
We gotta go. Let's go.
-來呀 -不行 你們得繼續解除武器
- Come on. - No. You need to keep working on it.
你打算干什么
What are you gonna do?
我得去干擾他們 否則大家都會被困在這里
I'll need to run interference or we're all stuck back here.
如果他們看到了我 就不會進到這里來
They won't keep coming if they see me.
只管解除這武器 給雷頓一個戰斗機會
Just disable it, and give Layton a fighting chance.
-魯絲… -派克先生 這是命令
- Ruth-- - That is an order, Mr. Pike.
現在由你來負責了
You're in charge now.
我信任你
I believe in you.
恭喜啊
Congratulations.
真不錯
That's nice.
是你
You.
沒錯 凱文 是我
Yes, Kevin. It's me.
你一直以來都在找的人
The one you've been looking for all this time.
你像只沒頭蒼蠅一樣到處瞎找
Running around like a chicken with your head cut off.
現在我來投降了
I'm surrendering.
我又冷又餓 所以 動手吧
I'm cold and I'm starving. So, come on.
不費吹灰之力 你就能當上英雄了
You get to be the hero without ever lifting a finger.
把她帶走
Take her.
最初我們有34個人
There were 34 of us to start,
依靠核電站的剩余電力竭力維持
eking it out on the plant's residual power.
都是韓國科學家
Korean scientists,
以及像我這樣的外國核技術人員
foreign nuclear technicians like me.
還有我們的一些家人
Some of our families too.
掠奪者死光之前 殺死了我們大約一半的人 然后…
Marauders killed about half of us before they died out. And then--
掠奪者
Marauders?
然后嚴寒或輻射中毒 奪走了其余人的性命
And then the cold or radiation poisoning took the rest of us.
我侄子當時是15歲
My nephew, he was 15 years old.
他是最后一個死的
He was the last to go.
他得了甲狀腺癌
He had thyroid cancer.
到最后 他在求我把他殺了
By the end, he was begging me to kill him.
那是大約四年前的事了
That was about four years ago.
在那之后…
After that…
我…
I…
我就沒有了時間的概念
I lost time.
不再抱有希望 不再去想
I stopped hoping, stopped thinking.
除了我之外還有其他人住在那下面
It's like someone other than me lived down there.
然后我看見了你
Then I turned my eyes on you.
我很抱歉地告訴你
I hate to tell you this,
在你與世隔絕期間 人類并沒怎么進化
but humankind hasn't exactly evolved in your absence.
你甘冒生命危險 甚至不顧理智 就為了救我
You pushed past what was safe, even sane, to rescue me.
為什么
Why?
我很高興自己那么做了
I'm just glad I did.
我們還是基本沒有信號
We're still basically blind.
我們上次到這里時還有衛星圖像的
We had picture last time we came out here.
-衛星信號在持續減弱 -說說其他選擇
The satellites continue to degrade. - Options?
等等 我們有其他選擇
- Wait, there's options?
我們直接回到主軌道上
We go back directly to the main line,
到時候 如果他們在我們前面 我們就會看到跡象
where we either see physical signs they're in front of us,
不然 我們就知道他們在后面
or we know they're behind us.
或者我們可以與主軌道平行前進
Or we parallel the main line,
希望信號會變好 能讓我們在衛星圖像上探測到他們
hoping the signal improves enough so we can glimpse them on the sat.
-選第二個方法 -遵命
- Second route. - Roger that.
你剛才那樣決定的依據是什么
And, um, you picked that based on what?
又看到了未來
Another vision?
不是 不上主軌道 我們會有更多選擇的余地 對嗎
No, I mean, there's gotta be more options off the main line, right?
對
Yeah.
她為我們犧牲了自己 所以現在我們得解除這玩意兒
She sacrificed for us. So now, we gotta kill this thing.
-好嗎  -這是筆記本電腦的連接口
- Okay? - The laptop patch is in here.
所以沒法黑入它的軟件
So we can't hack the software.
也許我們可以中斷電源 擾亂它的供電
Maybe we can disrupt the power supply, mess with it.
這好像是裝載程序面板
Looks like an arming sequence.
-它被激活了 -糟糕
- It's live. - Oh, shit!
-我覺得它處于全脈沖狀態 -是 我看到了
- I think it's at full pulse. - I can see that.
我沒法把它關了
I can't turn it down.
停不下來
It's not stopping.
好吧…
Well…
我早知道會是一個 對鐵路后勤具有敏銳洞察力的人
I knew it had to be someone with acumen for rail logistics.
但老實說 更令我欽佩的是
But to be honest, I'm more impressed with how low you went
你居然會如此屈尊 跟末等人混在一起
to grovel it out in the bowels.
我在盡量不辜負期望 先生
Well, I do try not to disappoint, sir.
如果你能保持忠誠該多好
If you'd only stayed loyal.
我是忠誠的
I am loyal.
我的忠誠給了比你更重要的東西 威爾福德先生 你全搞錯了
To something bigger than you. You've got it all wrong, Mr. Wilford.
這話我一直聽到 但我還是贏了
I hear that all the time, and then I win.
贏和領導是兩回事
Winning isn't leading.
光有忠誠還不夠
Loyalty isn't enough on its own.
還需要有愛 不是你享受的那種敬畏之愛
It has to come with love. And not the kind that you feed off.
而是無條件的愛 愿為每一個乘客犧牲
Unconditional love. Sacrifice, for each and every passenger.
-老天  -你不能忽視愛的力量
- Oh, God! - You can't ignore love.
你也無法預測它的力量
You can't predict it either.
好吧 我們得把這玩意兒 送出那扇門去
We gotta get this thing out that door.
-沒有開門的密碼 也沒防護服 -我在想辦法呢
- We don't have door codes or breach suits. - Uh, thinking. Uh…
第二年那場叛亂
Year two rebellion.
他們封了通勤車的門不讓我們上 但我們弄壞了鉸鏈
They sealed the subtrain doors on us, but we compromised the hinges.
快去
Go.
在這里
Here.
強壯男孩 準備好
Strong Boy, get it ready.
好 解除了 來吧
Okay. Clear. Come on.
動手吧
Let's go.
準備好了
Ready!
他們此刻正在為你準備門洞
They're preparing the port for you now.
我會確保他們把臂銬放高夾緊
I'll make sure they mount the cuff nice and high
讓你將來沒法裝假肢
where prosthetics are impossible.
反正我也不會戴假肢
Wouldn't wear one anyway.
來吧 你好了嗎
Come on. You got it?
好 快跑 姐妹 快跑
Okay, run. Run, sister, run.
快走
Go.
諷刺的是 我當初建門洞 只是一種虛聲恫嚇
The irony is, I built the ports in as an idle threat.
從沒想過要使用它們
Never expected to use them.
而你卻用了
You did.
13次
Thirteen times.
我愿意贖罪
I'll pay my penance.
把我的手臂凍掉吧
You can have my arm.
我很好奇那會是什么
- Whoa. - Whoa.
是電磁波
I wonder, what on earth could that be?
正在三角定位
Electromagnetic?
這是特征痕跡 一定是他們
Triangulating.
沒錯 是他們
Well, that's the signature. It's gotta be them.
在我們西側520公里處
Yes, it is. Five hundred and twenty kilometers west.
他們在主軌道上
They're on the main line.
這比在衛星圖像上找到他們強多了
That's a lot better than seeing them on sat.
是嗎 也就是說威爾福德看不到我們
Yeah? So it means Wilford can't see us.
我們比他有優勢
We got the drop on him.
-威爾福德討厭意外之事 -很好
- Well, Wilford hates surprises. - Good.
我們去給他一個“驚喜”
Let's go give him one.
我為你們做了一樣東西
I built something for you.
一樣本可以挽救無數性命的東西
Something that would have saved countless lives.
我們本可以不費一顆彈藥
We could have snuffed out Layton's pirate train
就毀掉雷頓的強盜列車
without firing a shot.
如今 就因為一個
Now, thanks to a rat
躲在管道中的叛徒
found hiding in the pipes,
這場戰爭爆發時
when this war comes,
你們將會有傷亡
you're all going to bleed.
都因為你 這場戰爭 又將回到原始的打斗方法
It's back to broadswords and shields because of you.
先生 好了 隨時可以行刑
Ready when you are, sir.
那就凍斷它吧
Let's get it bloody off then.
他們回來了
They're back. They're back.
-去戰斗崗位  -快走
- Battle stations! - Let's go!
去戰斗崗位 狗崽子們
Battle stations, you dogs!
快啊
Come on!
字幕翻譯： 黛拉